hello I'm your host David Bernard and my
guest today is Alex Prasad CEO of V1
Sports the leader in video golf swing
analysis software and seamless video
lessons on the podcast I talk with Alex
about the power of user segmentation
executing bold strategic shifts and why
imaginary customer conversations are
sometimes better than real ones hey Alex
thanks so much for joining me on the
podcast today really looking forward to
chatting thanks for having me David
super excited to share our story and
hopefully there's a learning or two
that's applicable to your listeners I
think there will be and that that's why
I wanted to have you on the podcast the
interesting thing about V1 Sports and
what I wanted to focus on was how and I
think so many apps are going to relate
to this it's like V1 Sports had amazing
early product Market fit and built a
great business around that and then went
through the Wilderness so let's kick it
off with what that early product Market
fit was and then we'll go through how
you came in and the things you did to
really get it back into a growth State
yeah so this company is over 20 years
old maybe closer to 30 which is crazy to
think about from a technology company
perspective not a lot lasts that long
basically right and the first Innovation
was being able to send video over the
Internet before really anyone else could
and applying it to this golf context so
I know today everyone's streaming 4K
four NFL games and their quad screens on
YouTube TV like hiking through the woods
right but that was not the case 20 plus
years ago right and then the second was
teating on that video so that
instructors could do a video analysis
whether in person or purely remotely and
send it right over the Internet so that
Innovation won roughly 30% market share
in North America amongst golf
instructors that's our B2B side of the
business Revenue cats working on the
consumer side we'll be talking mostly
about that but that became less
Innovative over time like every
Innovation right and so it won that
market share then there was a plateau
for a while in terms of growth so
especially on the consumer side learned
a lot of things to then start to
Kickstart whatever maybe phase two
whatever you want to call it growth and
not in a straight line not because we're
so smart but through a lot of trial and
error and a lot of learnings let's talk
through that so what was the state of
things when you join the company and
then let's start talking through that
early what it took to take this great
business but great business that had
kind of plateaued and get it back to
growth yeah well if you think about a
30-year Arc in technology I like to step
through phases so late '90s like who's
the best company
Ford and then maybe Microsoft right so
you go from let's sell a lot of stuff
Ford right like big expensive machines
to Microsoft let license software right
and deploy that so here's your CD and
install it on X number of computers
whatever right and then you start to
move I'm skipping like lots of Shades of
Gray here right you know into like a
subscription model but so when there's a
business that's of that age you have
remnants of each of those models and I
would say now we're like in a platform
model right with two sides of a
Marketplace and so on and so forth is
the best you know the best in quotes
right the most interesting thing and
maybe we've actually aged out of that
and now it's AI something right but so
yeah it was a puzzle because you had
vestages of each of these business
models which were the best practices at
the time lying about basically so we
needed to put a stake in the ground and
say which of these are we really which
is Antiquated by age or maybe not still
pertinent you think about these users I
mean we have high 80s per retention on
the B2B side of the business so these
guys are happy where they are they like
the thing and they don't really want
fundamental like that behavior
regardless of what we're doing to them
if you will means like I don't really
want to move right I'm happy where I am
thank you just keep delivering this
thing to me without disruption so we had
to look at those various business models
and choose one and then try to harmonize
around it and so especially on the
consumer side because the business
started purely B2B I would say the
strategy was I don't want to say
immature that sounds negative not the
point but it hadn't been focused on as
to like how do these pieces of the
puzzle go together right so not
surprising that opportunistic line of
business plateaued because it wasn't
really the focus as the starting point
it wasn't the Genesis of the company it
sounds like this is why you joined is
you saw that there was like a ton of
potential but what did the business look
like at that point like size and users
and you already mentioned 80% retention
which is insane yeah um so 30% market
share on the B2B business has not
changed a ton over the last they' been
with the company a little bit over four
years now with annual contract values
increasing that's the exciting story
there again not really our focus on the
consumer side again it's not being
critical right it's just like the order
of events was that the consumer thing
was opportunistic but it had never in my
opinion been thought about rethought
right once it reached a certain size so
because of that B2B Dynamic the focus
was really don't disrupt the inst
structor consumer relationship so some
instructors would have issues with the
fact that we could sell directly to
their customers that were on the
platform so we re thought that we made
some bold decisions which did create
some friction on that B2B side but we
basically switched from a fremium model
to a free trial model to simplify things
because fremium in my opinion in a
direct to Consumer business is probably
the most complicated monetization
strategy you can have and we got to be
really clear the a statement really
clear metrics really know where to draw
these lines right otherwise no pun
intended for a video telestration
company draw the lines Father Dad joke
right so but it hadn't that premium
strategy had been really I think
deployed more defensively to like keep
the pros happy if you will and still
today the pros students athletes can
join the platform are never going to
disrupt with a pay wall the interaction
between the two just like a touchstone
third rail you're never going to change
that it's a fundamental tenant of our
business if you will but we did rethink
that premium business model because the
thesis statement I think was fairly weak
to be blunt because it wasn't again it
was like an add- online of business
right it was not the main event so it
didn't get that level of thinking when
something's opportunistic you attack it
and you take the money that's there
right but that's very different than
being methodical and thinking about it
from scratch I want to interject because
I think a lot of ABS can relate and
maybe I need to help point this out but
so many apps if they're four five six
years old they don't have as much kind
of business strategy debt as VI sports
did but they probably have more than
they realize there's features that they
give away for free in their premium
strategy that maybe are higher value
that they should be putting behind a pay
wall there's ways they do things that
haven't been rethought in years and to
your point earlier things have changed
so much consumer willingness to pay via
subscription has changed onboarding
patterns have changed even like
willingness to pay higher prices are
surprisingly doing better and better if
you can deliver the value consumers are
more willing to pay higher prices for
software these days and I ever thought
consumers would be willing to pay for so
I think this is how if you're listening
in and you're like what does this like
golf app have to do with my business I
think this is the meat of it is that if
you've been around and your business has
plateaued at all or even if you've just
been around a bit and and are still
growing but want to grow faster like
taking a minute to re-evaluate some of
these like core aspects of the business
can produce incredible fruit so then
what was your process like how did you
gather data talk to users what did it
look like to figure out where those
opportunities were to shift the business
strategy well how much time do we have
so uh so I'm a corporate lawyer by
training and that you know perverted or
rewired or whatever adjectives you want
to use my brain um not a litigator no
one makes TV shows about corporate
attorneys but the first was just to
challenge our assumption so one of our
kind of it's not a core value but it's
just lurking outside of our core values
is nobody knows anything nobody right I
believe in experience shares I'm not
giving advice telling you our experience
here's what worked for us here's what
didn't apply it to your situation right
I don't know enough about your situation
to tell you right that my Approach is
right or wrong our approach is right or
wrong and then another kind of corporate
lawyer thing it's a logical syllogism
everything that we're doing what are
these implicit assumptions that we're
making to make decisions right and the
more time that passes the more dated
those like Bedrock assumptions are I
think one of the things that our team is
most proud of is it feels like we've
been in the last four years like 15
different companies completely
disorients our board which is a whole
different master class that someone
needs to give me but I view that as a
sign of progress and success so there's
lots of times we actually come back to
something that we may have done
previously and someone says well we
already tried that and I go whoa but
that was 18 months ago and think about
all the things we've learned let's go
back to so I'm a big fan of why are you
where you are can you go back and
critically evaluate that and are those
still true sometimes they might just be
truisms right and you might just say
check check check for instance for us
we're never going to make the student
pay to interact with their instructor
we're just not going to do it we go back
every once a while say well we could and
we go no but that's violates our core
Val you know and these people have a
long relationship with us we're not on
the pro side right we're not going to
disrupt that okay great that one hasn't
moved but what about these other things
so first for us was just go back to the
beginning and so free trial is just
simpler right we couldn't reconstruct
the thesis statement behind the premium
strategy so he said we need to make
things simpler and like get back to the
basics and by the way if you switch from
free trial or from premium to free trial
he going to make more money doing it you
might burn users story we can talk about
that and bad reviews whatever so there
are costs right so that was I want to
say I use the word easy a lot when I
think I mean simple that was simple it
was a or b you got to choose a door pick
one right but we decided basically to
retreat to move forward meaning there's
a lot of assumptions that are stacked
here and we don't really know how many
of these are true where's a simple place
to start to explain the universe that
we're living in and then proceed from
there and try to meticulously Brick by
Brick right lay these down so you have a
solid foundation and again we had such
high turnover a feature and a bug in
some ways and so institutional knowledge
got eroded to some extent it was easier
to do that because there weren't a lot
of sacred cows to us but also harder
because there was fear around well what
are we disrupting right because we
didn't have that full knowledge so that
was a start at least simplifying things
so we could list the four or five
assumptions that we thought we were
operating based on and then building off
of those yeah let's talk about that one
assumption then so it sounds like people
would open the app go through onboarding
and then be able to use the app and
certain features for free but was there
a premium tier at that point and what
did that look like and then when you say
switch to free trial is there no longer
any free usage of the app like you have
to pay to use the app like what data
what hypothesis did you have how did you
test it this is a transition maybe a lot
of I did this in my weather app so I've
already talked about this on the podcast
it was always intended to be short-term
but it worked really well in the short
term and so now I'm going to revisit
freemium once we get the product to a
certain point where the costs align and
things like that and we're in a
different market so like you said
experience is something you need to
learn from but not always directly apply
but anyway so yeah what did you mean by
freemium what did it look like in the
past and then what were the kind of user
research and data that kind of helped
inform the hypothesis and then how did
you validate that yeah so there's a
limited number of ways to improve your
golf swing just like fundamentally right
so you could work with someone that's
working with a coach right you can look
at your own swing with video we View
that as like foundational Elemental if
you want to improve any athletic thing
if you're not going to watch yourself do
it your level of seriousness about
improving is in our view because we're
thinking about our ICP right reduced
significantly so you're not really the
droids we're looking for probably right
and so video telestration goes along
with that and being able to look
repeatedly right the swing what's the
same what's different and what's a flaw
based on what I know or what we're
teaching you and then looking at
contents there's only three or four
things so we were allowing you to do
basic telestration in this premium but
not Advanced we thought that was way too
thin of a hair to slice right to split
there's no way you're either in or out
right and so when we still have way more
free users like 3x 4X like monthly
active users than we do paid basically
we just split up the constituent parts
right so they interacting with the pro
because the pros are generating about a
third of our new registered users on a
daily basis are coming from this
relationship so yeah we don't want to
disrupt this so what does that mean
today send videos to your coach go back
and forth with them interact with them
so the pros experience and your
experience hey there's this free app
this is what you use to interact with me
right let's go great but then there are
three quarters of the people that are
not coming through that channel right so
kind of teas segmentation we can talk
more about that but the three quarters
is where there's all this volume here
right 3x of volume so that's some of the
decision- making progress or process
just at the starting point who are you
and how did you come here right you came
through a pro or you didn't let's just
start there by the way when you're
trying to remodel the airplane while
it's flying doing some basic things like
that is hard don't get me wrong and
we're at a place now where we actually
think we do that well but that was like
the problem two years ago so that was a
starting point and then it was is it
reasonable to have to pay for that like
how much convincing are we doing with
the fremium tools and we can talk about
data and like when do you know to go or
not that's a good thing that we've
talked about previously David but that
was just Instinct I think largely like
when we don't know and we don't have
data to pointed out we try to retreat
make things simpler so that we like are
on more solid footing obviously not like
you burn a bunch of money or like stop
charging people or whatever right but
Retreat like it's too complicated it's a
golf app this isn't that complicated
right but if we don't understand what's
going on like adding in more and more
factors is not going to make it easier
it's going to make it harder right so
let's simplify this thing here's the
thing do you want it if you do you'll
pay us if you don't yeah should you have
a free trial sure try it out before you
buy right but we' really just Tred to
simplify as a starting point and that
was more Instinct and really not
Instinct about what the best reaction
would be in the market Instinct that we
didn't know so what are we supposed to
do if we're driving this vehicle we're
not in control of it what's the first
thing that you slow it down try to
understand what's going on because we
just keep going faster we're going to
hit something eventually right that's
the way we thought about that and then
as we got more fine-tuned certainly cly
data and instinct or whatever started to
come into play but at the start it was
simplify and respect the existing
relationships and I think we did that at
least what did the Gathering data look
like what did it look like talking to
users having conversations figuring out
how you could make this transition from
premium to the free trial that
transition versus I think it's about
maturity of a company like in where you
are that was more of a naked bet to be
blunt right we just knew what we didn't
know and so we had to make a leap but I
taught us a lot so we got all these
reviews of people who were in the
premium and all of a sudden now some of
their things right had to be paid and
you get these reviews and lots of onear
reviews so if you go back in the look at
the V1 Golf app in the iOS store and you
go back two years you a massacre right
and the responses were I've gotten this
for free for nine years and now I have
to pay for it I hate these guys I like
to say the more time I spend in other
people's shoes the more effective I have
been for the day cuz it really at the
end of the day it doesn't matter what we
want it matters what our customers want
right cuz we are trying to get our
customers to open our wallet and so I
like to a lot of calls that we have are
thinking things through and I'm not
saying anything what are you doing I'm
like I'm playing out I'm having a fake
conversation with a real person so I'm
having a conversation with this guy who
was leaving me a onear review saying I
got this free for nine years and now I
have to pay I don't think I have that
conversation in real life I think the
guy pays me you don't come to the bar
and get a free drink and come again next
week because the bartender likes you or
whatever and and go well yesterday or
last week you gave me a free drink so
I'm entitled to another one hey thanks
for the favor I'm going to pay for this
one for sure right in real life that's
what would happen so there were these
decisions where we understood there was
going to be friction to be blunt right
with users but that we were comfortable
with having that conversation when we
kind of War gamed it out people are
going to say that and I said not in
lacking empathy but so what if you're a
user who's looking to download this app
and four onear reviews and it's four
people who are upset that they had a
thing for free for almost a decade and
now they got to pay you know 60 bucks
and I understand the star rating like
that's important but we have to make
this shift here because I think for
every four that complain 10 are going to
subscribe and that's basically what
happened so there's a little bit of
blunt force there and that was uh I
guess the data in that case were more
mature now we don't have to make bigger
bets like that are a little bit bigger
leaps that we just hope but there the
data was war gaming out the
conversations right and trying to draw a
line between reasonable and unreasonable
which is completely subjective and which
conversations are we comfortable with
and which ones are we not and that was
one that we were comfortable with so you
really like burned the bridges because
this I had this exact same debate and I
landed on the other side of it for my
app that if I recall correctly part of
this decision was that as a business you
needed to make money like you needed to
move the dial financially and how do you
only made it free trial for new users
and grandfather Dan this like really
passionate long-term cohort of users you
knew you were going to leave too much
money on the table that you needed to
propel the business forward so it was
also like a business strategy decision
that like we need the money and we're
willing to take it on the chin to get
the cash flow we need to keep moving the
business forward yeah you know a lot of
people like called us greedy and if I
showed you the financial history of this
company that's the kind of hilarious
statement so yeah we we just made that
we just made that leap David I it's like
almost not a lot of thinking
required to explain the background
behind it we needed to do it for the
financial stability viability of the
company we just can't run if it's a
nonprofit it's a different story we're
still in a process of moving users over
a new pieces of software and sometimes
my team asks and I jump in to a
conversation and I say look like we're
running a business and these people are
working hard and they deserve to be paid
yeah so we offer a service if the
service isn't for you then find a
different service or don't choose not to
consume this service it's really that
simple maybe a different way of saying
it is you can't please
everybody much harder when those people
are already in the tent and some may
perceive it as you kicking them out
because you're changing the rules of the
game no one liked doing this to be super
clear I was like aha we got them you
know like let's squeeze these guys right
like not at all but you know to run a
viable business you're going to have to
make some decisions like that and I
would just say for as hard as it is in
your case right in mine with your
weather app it's no different I think
maybe a little bit of encouragement if
someone's looking down the barrel of
that to having set the right stuff in
the first place right yeah you say you
can only come into the theater if you
buy a movie ticket and then there's
people in the theater that didn't pay
they got in a back door or whatever you
going and seeking them out and saying
hey you're have to pay to be here that
is a conflict I get it you're less
likely to do it in that scenario than
the person at the front door but
fundamentally you should right like you
owe it to your shareholders you owe it
to your business and the people that
work there you can give them better
raises we can invest more in the product
for the users that are paying you can go
down that it's just kind of a matter of
fairness and that's not a word that's
really in my vocabulary but if you're
going to use our thing you got to pay
for it and if we change the permissions
if you will it also helps you know my
wife's a doctor I work for a golf
company it's like it's a golf app right
this is not kicking you out of the
hospital and you need life saving
procedure or something right wow but
then I guess it speaks to the core
product Market fit that you had these
users using those free features for such
a long for nine like you said nine years
somebody's using something for nine
years it's because it's delivering a ton
of value so you already talked about you
took it in the chin review wise but then
like how did it go was it like an
incredible success yeah I mean it grew
80 90% in 12 months or something thing
in terms of Revenue so yeah there was
just a lot of you could just do the math
right and you go wow there's a lot of
people that are using the heck out of
this that transition was about future
use it was not about holding people's
data hostage and so on and so forth and
one lesson I do think that we've learned
is that when we try to communicate a
nuanced message with three points the
first point is heard and the other two
aren't that's because people are busy
it's not like people are stupid that's
not what I'm saying but really
repeatedly we we' spent a lot of time
when we do these disruptive things
because this has been a turnaround
whatever the right word is right but a
rethink whatever the right phrases
there's been a lot of disruption and
we're are still disrupting in other ways
and other lines of business Etc to try
to get everything in the same strategy
on the right path and it's just funny
Maybe funny is the wrong word but how
repeatedly there will be a nuanced thing
that we're trying to say to folks and
really to take away one point and they
move on there's a recent example I SP
you the details so I guess my point is
if you're looking at one of these
decisions and you believe that the
aggressive decision is the right one
just know that the five weeks are going
to spend massaging well no there should
be a a fifth email right that
communicates this it is a little bit
binary right you're going to move
someone's cheese you're moving it that's
the way they're going to perceive it the
fact that you did it to the 95th
percentile versus the 55th percentile is
likely lost because they're upset that
the cheese has moved I don't know if
that's points to don't do that extra
work I'm just saying is unlikely that it
will be recognized if you move change
the game on someone right so just you
know buy or beware or fair warning you
won't be praised well I know you had to
do this but you did it in the best
possible way you're not going to get the
first part so you won't get the second
part so how did you communicate it
because that that's a a big deal again
why I wanted to have you on and why I
wanted to talk to this is because I
think there's a lot of apps out there
making decent money not growing
struggling that should not necessarily
go from premium to really burn the boats
and bridges there it would be hard for
me to in good faith recommend a lot of
apps go quite so dramatic but hey if
you're struggling it's a business you
need to make bigger bets and this was a
big bet so then if people are going to
make a big bet and make a big change
especially to existing users how did you
communicate it and sounds like you know
you've you've already shared one lesson
but any other lessons in that
communication that people could take
away from well I think the 8020 rule
applies right and I think fewer better
customers are better in general it's a
general rule if we could Pile in a
million users but they were all on the
knife's Edge at every renewal right and
we knew they didn't really get value we
call them zombies right like we got a
lot of zombie users out there that maybe
they forgot I mean that's a dirty secret
of the subscription business right is
that everyone has some percentage of
users this is why consumers revolt
against subscriptions and why businesses
like subscriptions they forget that they
even have the subscription right no one
wants to talk about that if you're in
our shoes but that's a part of the
business model right and one thing they
gave us confidence I think was this
which is that if you have fewer better
customers you're going to spend less
time trying to manage churn spend less
time just like worrying right about like
how tenuous your grasp is on these folks
what if the people that are really
getting value out of it have to pay for
the value right again that's a theme of
simplification right so that was what
I think gave us a lot of Solace and that
comes down to segmentation and trying to
understand your customers and if you
believe you have customer lots of
customers that actually love the product
you should charge a fair price for it
and if you're worried so so worried that
this kind of applies to price increases
too right so so worried that a 10% price
increase or and maybe not today's but
the last couple years inflationary
environment is going to run off all your
customers I would just encourage you to
think through why
and is it because you don't have
conviction that your product is really
like solving one of these people's
problems right or your user's problems
and if that's the case the problem isn't
the price increase the problem is Right
understanding those customers and
delivering the value right I think this
comes down to trying to treat people
like they are people and not users right
because we have all this data and
thousands of users and so on and so
forth everything becomes a spreadsheet
but we forget that fundamentally it's
people and so I like to spend like I
said a lot of time on other people's
shoes but then also a lot of time
pretending like these interactions are
happening in real life oneon-one does
that make sense would you do that in
real life look everyone knows it's
software it's programmed to give you
this answer that's fine but if it
doesn't feel right or doesn't mimic the
human behavior the chances of success
are lower in my opinion right so again
to the person who has that issue with
the N9 years free whatever let's play
this out in real life are we okay with
that are we okay okay with other people
over hearing
that answer is yeah right whatever
percent of people are not going to like
it right and that will create that
Snowball Effect that you're so worried
about sure but most people we think
that's reasonable these guys are working
they're delivering a service and they're
not getting paid for it they should get
paid for it probably right segmenting
your customers understanding where
they're coming from and what they're
doing and then are we scratching the
itch that they have right can give you a
lot of confidence alth that being said I
don't feel like every day I wake up and
go I don't think we understand this well
enough right it's not like you reach a
point oh we got it we figured them all
out mission accomplished we've landed on
the moon whatever no if you're not
paranoid about that all the time but
that's the root cause issue of
everything right Are you delivering the
value to these people that they feel
like they can't live without and if you
are you got a lot of freedom and
flexibility do a lot of things so our
average user spends 21 minutes a month
in the app or monthly act abusers that's
a ton right which is not a license to
abuse them but it is okay these people
get it and they're going to be retained
at a high level it's something to build
off of right and the ones that are in
and out real fast or not using it that
that level we want to understand why but
we also know that a lot of those people
are like not savable not the ideal
Customer because there are ideal
customers over here what's working for
these people let's really drill in here
and understand and apply it to more with
the understanding that these people
might only be 20% right everyone is not
your ideal customer you teed up uh
segmentation which which I do want to
dig into but but just one more time
restating the question what did you tell
them though this is the like practical
takeaway for folks if you're going to
make a big change to the way you operate
to asking people to pay did you just say
like you know this business will fail
and you will not have an app you need to
start paying and then like did you do
that through on the pay well like brass
tax like how did you actually implement
this change and communicate with users
about the change yeah that's a funny
that's what you wanted to say for sure
this is a for-profit business and we
can't subsidize you and all those things
we said it nicer but there wasn't a ton
there was hey look Yeah by you investing
in right this subscription we can
deliver a better product kind of period
and that goes back to my lesson of
everything that comes after that they're
not listening to I have to say total
personal opinion take or leave I
disagree with the no explanation change
which I've seen more and more of lately
where people like your price is going up
or or here's a link to your new billing
statement right and then you click in
there and realize that the price
increase that does again you and me
David right I say that to you or like I
we have an interaction like you buy a
service or product for me in real life
and I just don't tell you that the price
changed aren't you going to walk out
when you look at the receipt later or
whatever be like hey what the heck this
used to be right and now it's that's not
cool and if I had just said hey David
you're I'm your dry cleaner the shirt's
five bucks now not three bucks because
of all these reasons You' been like yeah
okay but I've been going to you for
forever and I like you and whatever so
it is what it is right yeah I had this
exact experience recently so I had a HB
contractor come did some work the bid
was
$2,100 yeah he finishes up I pay he
leaves and then I looked at my credit
card statement and it was $3,000 $900
more than the bid and he they never
explained to me and I've been like
calling them and like about ready to do
a charge back on my credit card just to
get their attention to your point it's
treat people like humans and like having
just had that experience I very much
relate
to not just increasing the price just to
increase the price and actually
communicating about it so and then it
see sounds like you had some more to go
on that yeah well it just I think it
comes back to the fear right so let's
put ourselves in the shoes of the
contractor or the hbac company right
they set an expectation it says a lot
more about them right and like what's
going on in their head and I get it I
have sympathy for being in that position
because happened to me many times I set
one expectation and I can't deliver on
it that's crap it's like one of my least
favorite things in life but like trying
to skate through is just never going to
to be it's just delaying the pain
basically right they delayed the pain
until my charge back right but it would
have been felt so much better just for
them to say hey look it was a bigger job
than we thought it took me longer here's
why maybe it took me longer because I'm
not very good you don't have to say that
part right but this is why and that's
the point to the three or third fourth
or fifth thing no one's listening anyway
right you're going to hear oh man it's
900 more bucks but at least he told me
right and now that expectation has been
reset in a negative way to me to be sure
but it's just kind of the right way of
doing things my wife likes to say I'm
too honest a lot of the time like weird
comment but I get it but it's because
I'm not smart enough to keep track of
the lies basically right like I'm not
smart enough I need a really big notepad
yeah so it's just easier and simpler and
more genuine and people will appreciate
it that would be another thing about
segmentation is you'll listen to the
squeakiest wheels but don't over listen
to them right it's important to be
tracking that for sure and asking a lot
of wise and see if you can even get them
so maybe the inverse of the like if you
give four reasons only going to hear I
moved your cheese and maybe the start of
the first explanation but like a lot of
time we're building towards a call right
or the actual conversation with the
squeaky wheel and then again we just
playact it out are we comfortable in
that scenario do we feel proud is the
wrong word but do we feel okay and
comfortable in it right well I can't
believe that you're making me pay for
for something that I've used for forever
and I've never paid for I'm like yeah I
can right like where's the other place
that's giving you you know a free house
or a free car or a free whatever right
you say it nicely but you try to get to
the why and if you get to a why that's
like bizarre you go okay that's on you
not on me moving on right right
sometimes you get to a real why you go
oh someone else set this expectation
that we didn't even know or what right
and you go oh wow okay thanks for
sharing that with me yeah Our advice was
always and you can't do it on the
consumer side but as we've moved stuff
on the pro side I always tell my team
that you have complete and total
autonomy to make it right but there are
some guard rails and we'll set them
ahead of time you can't use a thing for
free for forever you got to pay
something right but if you can reach a
reasonable deal we don't want people to
leave angry right if you can avoid it
but you have to at least move the person
towards the goal right so I'd love to
have a Playbook and a hard and fast
black and white rulle for everything and
there's a policy there's a policy but
more we just have a really great team we
trust them to make decisions and diffuse
situations but not diffuse them at our
expense right you can treat someone like
an adult and compromise and reach
somewhere that's you know at least a
step in the direction but yeah you have
to have the tough conversation you can't
just not have it it's been so fun diving
into this I didn't expect to get quite
so deep on like product psychology it's
ultimately and I love the way you keep
bringing it back to these are other
human beings on the other side of it and
I think that's where a lot of folks in
the subscription app industry are maybe
heading the wrong direction currently
like over optimizing their pay wall on
data and not putting themselves in the
user shoes of what does that actually
feel like and then how do you to your
point diffuse that situation through
communicating effectively and if your
goal is just to make as much money as
you can as quickly as you can sure go
for it but if you're like trying to
build a truly great business it's going
to stand the test of time and to your
point earlier which I loved have users
who care enough to pay have the users
that matter not just a bunch of zombie
users who forgot that's a good
subscription business I think a lot of
people these days are building toward
not having a great subscription business
they're over optimizing on price and
other conversion metrics that do bring
in a lot of those very poor quality
users that aren't going to new and the
magic of subscription app businesses is
those users who are going to stick you
with you for a decade and be willing to
pay for the value that you're creating
not just tricking people via dark
patterns and other stuff because then
you're just going to bleed out those
users on the back end and then you're
pissing off the people who would
otherwise become like your really
amazing like 10e users so anyways it's
been really great diving into the like
psychology aspect of building a great
business by like caring about the people
and the other end yeah I think it's look
the promise of
SAS and subscription businesses is a
scalability in the margin that's why
most people get into it right as opposed
to a professional service or something
else right restaurant has like 0.5% or
1.5% you know like really really hard
businesses and like the faster you run
not necessarily the faster you get ahead
so get that but there's something and we
fall into it all the time myself
included that breaks your brain in ter
terms of running such a business is
you're so hyper to get to the
scalability that we forget that the way
to learn is inherently
unscalable activities we call it the
hamster wheel someone called it to me
the gerbal power whatever metaphor you
want to use build the gross manual maybe
bespoke process first right and learn
from it and do it so get a little bit of
data have hypothesis get a little bit of
data pay wall is whatever right to prove
the point okay this pay wall is doing
better than that pay wall why opinions
enter now right and then attest those
opinions and choose the best one we get
so obsessed with well that's not
scalable well how do we know because we
don't even know where we're going yet
the idea isn't inherently scalable or
not the execution of it is so test the
idea purposefully in an experimental way
and then what a great problem I I like
to talk about great problems let's let's
create good problems what a great
problem we have a thesis that we're
doing some manual gross lots of hamsters
running on wheels or whatever thing and
it's working and now we just have to
make it scalable like how do we take
this manual thing and write it into the
software how we take this manual thing
and not make it a survey that zaps
somewhere but make it a core part of our
back end right great that's great if all
those are the problems we're working on
every day I'd be on vacation 24 hours a
day right that'd be great we'd only
those are that's fantastic right this
works now we just have to scale it up
again in this industry we get so
obsessed with the scalability part that
we miss like we just skipped because we
reject any idea that we can't
immediately see the through line to
scalability well gee whiz there's a lot
of good ideas and talking to people's
not scalable we just talk to a lot of
people and that will create a hive mind
that will be useful so yeah this is a
pattern that we saw the same with
planning right like there's all these
pain in planning at the outset if you
ever seen squiggly lines and then you
know pain and how much planning is
involved no pain at the beginning if you
don't plan but lots of pain later
similar Dynamic but again everyone falls
into the Trap but I think particularly
people that are attracted to sass
because they see that opportunity Rome
wasn't built in a day to use a cliche
but all these overnight success stories
when you start to learn about them it's
like they took them eight years to
figure this stuff out right it explodes
onto the scene and it wasn't because
they built this super scalable thing
eight years ago because if it was super
scalable eight years ago they wouldn't
have just come onto your radar today
right so yeah that's just a not a flaw
and logic but just a pattern that you
know I find ourselves getting sucked
into all the time that just pump the
brakes for a second can we learn as much
as we possibly can now first don't worry
about how we scale it we'll figure that
part out because it'll be worth it
because we'll be the courage of our
convictions if you will what I see over
and over again in the data is apps do
come out of nowhere but they come out of
nowhere with dark patterns with not
actually delivering on value but they're
really good at paywall optimization
onboarding optimization but not really
good at building a great product yeah
the execution is there but not the
product Market fit yeah it's crazy yeah
and so then and then they grow and then
they just hit a cliff and then die die
die die die because like you're saying
it's like that's that's sass it's people
actually have to use the product for you
to get value over time and if all you're
doing is converting folks and not
retaining them then you're not building
a good business so but part of
understanding those users and I did want
to transition to segmentation is it part
of being able to Think Through who these
users are what they like how to
communicate to them how to most
effectively sell them is understanding
who they are so talk about how you think
about user segmentation and
understanding who those users are again
not the expert right like just an
experience share what we've learned and
you I don't know if this stuff works
that we're doing you we we'll find out I
guess right I really mean that this is
my my first rodeo in this role and in
this industry so maybe I'll be better my
family say you'll do better next time
doesn't matter if it's a good thing or a
bad thing we'll do better next time like
you'll know more you know U you do
something really good like you'll do
better next time and if you do something
bad like you'll do better next time so
this comes back to what we were talking
about earlier in just War gaming out
real life conversations but we reached a
point where yeah we had plateaued again
if you will and I think we're still
actually there to be completely honest
we got that growth of changing the
business model great and Okay now what's
the next thing oh man right and it
really we again rechallenged our
assumptions it came back to what do we
know about these people the answer was
like not a lot right we're looking at
their user where are they clicking and
why and how much time are they spending
on the screen I'm like man but the data
can tell us where to look but it can't
tell us the story right of the people
and so we started treating the app like
you were walking into a golf shop or
like you were walking into a retail shop
and started asking and were really
worried about the tradeoff between right
straight line onboarding and get the
person in right and scalability and
whatever and creating more friction the
more I talk to other people in the space
and people that I respect talked a lot
about positive friction and that you're
going to filter out bad users sooner and
the ones that do make it through you're
going to be a lot more confident with
that you have product Market fit Etc so
that's basically what we've done and we
started asking people like why are you
here by the way we're going to get way
better at asking that question because I
think we're only scratching the surface
but what we found was that hundreds of
people a week maybe 10 15% of all the
new registered users wanted to find a
coach and believe it or not even though
we talked about coaches and the golfers
we didn't really facilitate that well we
were facilitating existing relationships
not building new ones and so just as a
starting point there when we started
asking the question why are you here
there's only four or five ways to
improve as we were talking about earlier
one of them is to meet a coach is that
interesting to you we've battled a lot
about are we collecting information are
we pushing them towards a result and
again I don't have answers there but we
found out there's a significant number
of people that are actually even though
we're not putting it into the universe
that this is a place defying to coach
that's what they're here for so what if
we gave it to them and it turns out
those people even though that's not what
this plus Golf Plus premium if you will
right subscription gives you are a much
higher likelihood to subscribe as well
so I think on the next Rodeo Whenever
Wherever that is that's fundamental in
first is some sort of onboarding
sequence where you just ask what are you
doing here what do you think like on a
you know on a B2B business right you
would ask what's your me of success
right super important customer success
question same thing here on the consumer
side and it sounds so basic simple but I
it took us years to get to the
conclusion we should just ask I mean we
looking at all this data and it's like a
lightning bolt one day like why don't we
just ask are people going to leave
because they got one minute or less
right survey of just these fundamental
basic things maybe actually probably yes
at the fringes but these are people that
were not your ideal customers anyway
right so like when we look at the whole
like you know least common denom minator
not just in math but like is a thing and
limboing to it is not going to get the
rewards are going to come from that
those icps or that 8020 rule it's not
going to come from optimizing everybody
because then you're going to dilute the
product for the people that are your
icps and you're going to be playing to
the crowd that's unlikely to subscribe
anyway and that kind of goes back to a
confidence that is this a tool that
actually has value and people really
want and if the answer is yes the total
rful Market could be too small Etc but
think about that phrase total
addressable Market you can't address an
non-addressable market so don't try to
you know right attack the people that
like fundamentally aren't really that
into you to begin with so that was a a
breakthrough for us just ask and then
then we say well how do we make this
more straight line you go back and forth
It's not black and white but again like
a fear of asking came up implicitly in
our conversations because they thought
you'd run people off who you were going
to run off by asking them why are they
here I mean people not people that are
really into it and want to be here right
I love the framing of what is your
measure of success I think in
consumer we don't think about that as
directly so I do think about like jobs
to be done that's a famous framework
that I've kind of like used as a mental
model to understand user behavior and
then speaking of my weather app I I
think all the time about there's a job
to be done of like when is it going to
rain do I need a raincoat do you know do
I need to take my umbrella do I need a
jacket today like that that's one job to
be done but there's actually so many
other jobs to be done in even something
as seemingly simple as a weather app and
that's why some people gravitate towards
some weather apps that that just tell
you in the morning do you need an
umbrella like I think there was an app
called Poncho that its whole thing was
just like do you need a raincoat today
or not and then it sends you a push
notification in the morning and that's
like finding a really clear measure of
success the measure of success is that I
don't get caught out in the ring without
my Rin Cod or umbrella and then
understanding that measure of success
then helps you build the better product
to meet that measure of success and so
even something as seemingly simple as a
weather app has all these different jobs
to be done has all these different
measures of success and understanding
from your users what that measure of
success is then focuses you one like you
were saying on the more valuable users
who are going to pay for it and then
potentially even seg men in those to
show them the higher premium tier if you
have two different tiers or there's
different ways to optimize that into a
better experience for them getting the
premium tier versus the lower tier
because that's what's going to actually
deliver for them and they're not the
kind of user that's going to be happy
with the non- premium tier even if that
on an AB test the non- premium tier
converts better but you're missing the
forest for the trees because there's
some users who aren't going to find
success in that non- premium tier or
whatever and so just by understanding
these measures of success as you framed
it and asking what that measure of
success is can help tremendously and
doing that onboarding like you said it
can be tricky and create friction but
where's the payoff and that the payoff
can be tremendous yeah I mean easier the
higher the ACV is right to create more
friction because you understand that the
payoffs there and $70 a year now is our
Golf Plus subscriptions that's not high
ACV by anyone's definition but yeah I
mean that's maybe a good summary of this
conversation is these aren't black and
white
things and you're going to keep moving
the
dials more of this less of this right we
want to decrease the flow because we
need higher value oh wait no that's too
much because look at all the breakage
right so open it up a little bit and
then yeah measure of success is
obviously the way we're thinking about
it and then the question is how can you
ask that question in the right way to
elicit the right response that's the
really hard part you can't just say
what's your measure success what do you
mean what's a measure ex I don't I don't
understand right so the why are you here
and again that goes back to like can you
do it in real life first in your head
fake right coming to the golf shop what
are you you know what are you looking
for do you want this you want that and
so for us you're coming to the golf
Improvement store how do you want to
improve well I don't know okay well
there's these couple menu choices and
then again Shades of Gray art not
science we had this conversation because
we I think been successful in thinking
about that metaphor you walked into the
golf improvement store what would you do
next if you're the clerk if you will
greeting the person coming in the person
says I want to improve this way but
maybe we want them improve a different
way because we can make more money doing
that right or it's a higher value do you
just go with the flow of the customer do
you say well there's also this other
option just so you're aware and is that
friction towards the goal that they
stated right these are all you don't
know right and that's where the data
comes in right because you can measure
those things those are little
incremental improvements changes but our
position total opinion land as I like to
say statement was make them understand
that other options are there right
that's why you put a menu in front of
someone even if they say like they know
exactly what they want to order like
well here's a menu just in case you know
if you want to peruse it but that's
again it's not black and white that's
not I can't write a book and I chat shbt
can't give you the syllogism of right
how to get that done it's Instinct right
but using the data to fuel the Instinct
you know if like three people stick
their tongue out at you and run out of
the store because you say I don't care
that you said you wanted this I'm going
to give you that you're like well okay
don't do that right you have to modulate
based on re
so yeah all hard problems to solve you
kind of alluded to it earlier that in
golf there is a higher ACV but then also
probably a higher willingness to pay
higher comparable like we've talked
about this on the podcast a lot
weightlifting apps going to the gym is
60 bucks a month hiring a personal
trainer is 60 bucks a session or 120 a
session if you're at a fancy gym and so
how do you think about pricing and to me
that almost sounds low you can hardly
get on a course these days for 80 bucks
and you're only charging them $80 a year
when they're in a hobby that's probably
5,000 a year 10,000 a year I mean if
they're like really going for it and
buying new clubs all the time and have a
pro teaching them and they're traveling
the world to golf and you're only
charging 80 bucks a year how do you
think about that you're right it is just
math at the end of the day how many
people willingness to pay is super high
for the most Avid and then you move into
less Avid and then how much are you
willing to pay Fierce competition
because the underlying tool the video
analysis is largely commoditized right
so there's a downward pressure at this
stage right downward pressure on pricing
it's not like there's not a lot of other
ways to get that job done on both sides
of the business it's been about how do
we make this you position it as the
first step the fundamental step the step
that needs or a place for you to grow
and start again the horsepower here is
largely commod or the engine is largely
commoditized so what are the things
around us this is the only place where
you can a but BC and D as well right so
if you're going to compare a against
anybody else Apples to Apples but we can
do b c and d so if you really want to
grow and improve you want more options
to do that in a place to grow over time
that applies to both sides of our
business so that's why you should start
here because it's not a dead end right
it's not a short dead end alley right
like you can continue to grow into
different ways when you're ready for
that and a is the same as everyone
else's a that's the way we've thought
about it yeah hard to split it's funny
most golf companies are
selling I don't know if most is the
right word but a lot of golf companies
are selling things that are a lot higher
ticket price right and so I found that
many of in any industry the most
exciting businesses is a lot of people
model off of those businesses they're of
often High ticket price items right but
if your ticket price is a fraction of
that you can't mimic their behavior
because unit economics just aren't there
right so if you're selling golf clubs
you got two or three extra zeros a year
if you will right versus what we're
selling you can't take that business
model and then apply it to something
that's 100th of the cost you can't do it
right so you have to approach it in a
fundamentally different way so you can
talk about expansion Revenue
opportunities of which for us on the
consumer side are fairly limited but
yeah that initial get in the door price
that's opinion statement I don't know
advice is stuff but I don't think the
optimal price is the maximal to get the
most Revenue out of just that first bite
at the Apple if you will if that word
salad made sense right because I think
most would aspire to put a software
product out where they can go on a
journey that the more you use it the
more value you get out of it and then
therefore the more value You' pay for it
right so the revenue maximizing over the
lifetime of the customer price may be
artificially low versus if you were only
selling one tier and one set of options
you would put that at the highest price
possible basically right you just do the
m at that stage and then for all of us
right thinking about ACV and renewal
rates Etc right you're trying to it's a
multivariable equation obviously but
really we learned this on the B2B side
where we didn't really have expansion
Revenue opportunities for a long time
once you have them it radically changes
the way you think about that first step
the first opening of the wallet because
I just want to get you in and start to
interact and learn more about you yeah
you're paying something for the service
but there's this growth pattern that
could be really interesting for you and
for us right that's another courage
lowercase C but courage of convictions
kind of decision because I think most
people Dan Martell SAS Academy calls it
commission breath right if you were
selling cars or boats or houses sure
because it's likely one transaction
going to do with these people it's not
repeat players right it's you're trying
to maximize the value of that one
transaction but for us which I think is
a largely socially beneficial Dynamic if
you will it's a repeat game so take the
guy for as much as he can right off the
bat is probably unlikely to be longterm
the most effective strategy and see that
that goes counter to what so many people
are thinking I mean things we've
discussed on the podcast and other
things is when the data says a higher
price works you go for the higher price
and you scale up but again it's like
what business are you building are you
building advertising Arbitrage where
you're just going to find as many users
who are willing to pay as possible and
charge them the maximum Revenue possible
today to keep that flywheel going or are
you looking for those better users that
you're going to build a relationship
with and have more opportunity to
monetize them over time and I think I
already talked about this on a past
episode but there's this incredible
chart that Dimitri the founder of Flo
shared on LinkedIn that shows and I
think it was actually also shared in
Eric Crowley's GP B Hound consumer
subscription report and it it shows that
over time Flo has actually had net
revenue retention increase where the
initial cohort retention in year one is
like 60% Revenue retention and then it
actually goes up year after year after
year because they are selling more into
those users users upgrading to a more
premium tier users buying other features
that they didn't get with that initial
payment and that's a fantastic business
that's why Flo raised at a over billion
dollar valuation and had competition to
get into the round whereas if you're
over maximizing that initial and you
have really bad turn and you don't have
any kind of industry above Benchmark
Revenue retention you're in a much worse
place as a business moving forward so I
love that framing you mentioned in there
commoditization of the primary
technology of V1 Sports and this is
something I think we all are seeing in
the consumer subscription space which
means a lot of folks the last few years
have jumped in and and there's a lot of
commoditization going on in our space
and I thought it was interesting that
rather than pointing to the willingness
to pay and all the price comparisons in
the golf industry you went right to our
primary technology is commoditized and
just the blunt reality that you live in
that you would recognize that and then
so directly state it but then you must
be thinking okay that primary technology
is now commoditized what about our
product is differentiated that we can
charge for and then what new products
can we build that are highly
differentiated that we can increase that
Revenue over time by adding these addons
and new features and new things that
people will be willing to pay for that
aren't commoditized maybe like a great
point for folks is if you have a
commoditized product you probably do
want to aim for that more kind of
industry standard pricing but then
figure out where you can really
differentiate and that's where you
charge and maybe the differentiation is
the whole product and then you can fight
back against that commoditization and
charge a higher price but you got to
actually be differentiated to charge
that higher price so how are you
thinking about that differentiation I
really believe that execution wins nine
times out of 10 for sure so even if your
internal don't say it out loud
assessment is that your product is very
similar or commoditized versus others I
do think you can have confidence that
executing the competition is a path to
some level of success just probably not
a,x growth success right there's some
hard limit there
but if you're okay with whatever percent
growth a year so it just depends what
your goals are probably you can start
with that and everything falls after
that what's the point what are your
goals but yeah I mean we've tried really
hard and just like the entire Journey
it's been about what's unique to us so
this
answer again the execution of this
really hard really complicated but the
answer was fairly obvious which is this
unique position that we're in almost
100,000 monthly active users at high
tide every summer spending that 21
minutes a month and all these
instructors I wonder if they want to go
and the answer was yes right so that's
what we're really working on and again
the starting point was why are you here
and then when they started telling us
that was a big thing hey I want to find
an instructor I would take help from an
instructor oh guess what the more people
that want help from an instructor the
more instructors want to be here unlock
right and are we optimized that not even
close we're trying very hard to execute
on that so for us it was fairly obvious
again it was us again looking around the
room of the resources that we have say
well what are unique resources that we
have but yeah I mean I would I guess to
put myself in a different scenario cuz
ours is unique if you had just the b2c
business right so these spare parts
aren't lying around just make sure
you're getting the most out of what
you're doing would be you know again
trying not to give advice but from that
execution piece even if the product is
commoditized can you out execute the
competition with focus and diligence the
answer I think is yes 99% of the time if
you're built like you are David or me
like can you focus on something for
longer than two hours no way longer than
2 minutes maybe right most organizations
you multiply that difficulty by many
people really can't so not that talk out
of both sides of our mouths and don't
Focus too much on conversion or whatever
at the outside then but also really
focus on it if you're convinced of two
things I think you're in trouble one you
have a commoditized product and there's
lots of competitors to do something
similar and two you've rung the rock for
every ounce of efficiency everywhere
around you I don't think most people are
in that boat it certainly make marketing
Etc more challenging and so you do need
to at least come up with a genuine this
is why we're different right statement
even if it's on soft things like we
actually answer the phone for support or
we've been in the business for a long
time so you should trust our brand you
can find those differentiating factors
even if the core may be very similar but
yeah I would challenge that the
assumption that if you're commoditized
or you think your thing is commoditized
that that's the end of the road because
I guarantee that there are ways you can
execute better there's lots of room to
run there again if your goal is to be a
trillion dollar market cap company yeah
your thing has to be the latest Nvidia
chip don't get me wrong right and that
just is what it is but there's lots of
space between no growth and Bonkers
growth to move and you might just have
to be realistic that it's not going to
be a th X every year but if it's 10%
every year 20% every year reliably
because you keep getting better at what
you're doing that might be a happy spot
but yeah obviously highest and best is
find a new thing and make it better but
that's a shiny object syndrome that lots
of us are prone to fall into yeah but I
think this whole podcast has been a
great lesson on how to act actually find
that differentiation is think about
users have those conversations in your
head with actual user I've never done
that that I'm going to that's one key
takeaway I'm going to do it's like I
have done user testing I have had those
user conversations but I don't regularly
look at a feature look at a dialogue box
that I'm creating look at marketing copy
and then picture somebody standing in
front of me and make it into a
conversation like I think it's a really
great way to operate as you're building
a consumer product is to like put that
consumer right in front of you and think
about it so I think this whole whole
conversation has been a great way to
focus you on not chasing that shiny
object syndrome but actually finding the
things that users care about so thanks
for sharing all your lessons in getting
there and growing and burning the ships
and everything you've done along the way
because I I think this is going to be
super helpful to folks so yeah thanks
thanks so much for sharing thanks for
having me David I love to reflect and
it's a work in progress and there's no
destination that's been arrived at just
to be super clear and anything you
wanted to share as we wrap up you have
any job openings that that might be a
good fit for folks or or any way the
audience can interact with you or help
you if anything any of this was
stimulating you want to have a
conversation experience share whatever
Alex at V1 Sports pretty easy yeah just
Reach Out happy chat happy to learn more
from you know more people in this space
well thanks so much for for joining me
Alex this was so much fun thanks
David thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
you and your favorite podcast player you
can also stop by chat. sub club.com to
join our private community